

<?xml-model href="../rsrc/schema/gazetteer_schema_translation.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>


<translation>
    <loc_sec id="47">
        <heading>Qarakol Province</heading>
        <ts>The second <glossed>province <gloss type="translit">wilāyat ū ḥukūmat</gloss></glossed>
            of the provinces of Bukhara is the <glossed>district<gloss type="translit"
                >qaẓā</gloss></glossed> of Qarakol. Its distance from Bukhara the Noble is seven
                    <glossed>farsakhs<gloss type="comment">A "farsakh" is an old Persian unit of
                    measurement, around 4 miles.</gloss></glossed>. This province is vast and
            populous. The denizens of this province are all well-off, and all of them <glossed>have
                    livestock<gloss type="literal">have herds</gloss></glossed>. In the past, this
            province was even vaster; [but then] in the span of a century, sand enveloped a quarter
            of the province from the west, north, and south. Nevertheless, [Qarakol is among] the
            most propserous of the provinces. Due to a <glossed>lack of learning<gloss
                    type="translit">ʿadam-i ʿilm</gloss></glossed>, the population does not engage
            in trade. However, in this province there are many individuals who own more than one or
            two million Tanga [a currency], and many of them are even wealthier than the Bukharan
            merchants. Qarakol [sheep] skins are well known for their high value, and are even more
            prized in Europe (Ūrūpā ū Farangistān) than in Bukhara, and are obtainable in greater
            numbers and earlier [in the season] than in other provinces. </ts>
        <ts>In this province there is: one brick and morar (lit. "stone," sangīn) madrasa and one
            qārī-khāna (Qur'an reading center); adjacent to the fortress (Qurghan) are seven sufi
            lodges (khānaqāh) (both wooden and stone) and eighteen mosques. [The province] comprises
            809 villages, which contain 150,000 residents. </ts>
        <ts>Water in this province is inadequate, but despite that, agriculture is good. In a bad
            [drought] year, the land is irrigated, which leads to a strong harvest. </ts>
        <ts>To the west of this province is a salt mine, located four farsakhs from the center (az
            markaz-i qażā-yi ān). Every year around ten thousand individuals beset by illnesses of
            the nerves (amrāż-i ʿaṣabānī), such as [check specific terms] come to this salt mine for
            treatment. Even foreigners consider the mineral water from this mine to be superior to
            others. </ts>
        <ts>To the east of this province, in the territory of Paykand, there is a ruin in the sand.
            This is in fact the original, ancient city of Bukhara, and Abdallah bin Ziyad [an Arab
            general during the 8th (?) century] fought there. Now all of the walls and fortresses
            [suwar ū qalʿa ū arg] and some of the buildings still remain, but - in the words of the
            holy Qur'an -
            <flag>???</flag>
             . The people of Paykand excavate this area to find silver and gold coins, and other old
            artifacts, and in this manner make their living. The reason for the ruination of this
            province is twofold: first, the Arab armies devastated it during the conquest [of the
            7th and 8th centuries]; second, sand has enveloped it. For these two reasons, the
            province has fallen into ruin. </ts>
    </loc_sec>
    <loc_sec id="46">
        <heading>Ghijduvan</heading>
        <ts>The third province is the district (qażā) of Kharqānrūd. This province of Ghijduvan is
            an ancient city and great land. </ts>
        <ts>This province is long; it spans from the plain (qir) of Bābā Dūghī to the hill (tall) of
            Ghandak. East-West it is nine Farsakhs of pasture and farmland. </ts>
        <ts>Inside the fortress (Qurghan) there are a number of ancient structures, including a
            stone bathhouse, as well as a stone Sufi lodge (khānaqāh) at the head of the shrine
            (mazār) of Shaykh Tāj al-Dīn. Inside the city there are seven other mosques.
            <flag>REVSIT rest of section</flag>
        </ts>
        <ts>Most of the people are Kazakhs of Nur-Ata who come to this province to work; they do not
            go to Bukhara itself. </ts>
        <ts>The people of this province
            <flag>are constantly injured from their penchant for fireworks</flag>
             . Every year several individuals are killed or injured. Nevertheless, they persist in
            this activity.
            <flag>FINISH section</flag>
        </ts>
        <ts>Across five hundred and sixty villages there are 715 mosques and twenty-six
            congregational mosques. </ts>
        <ts>In the village of Bāy-Khātūn, at the fut of a great mulberry tree on the road to
            Bukhara, there is a footprint shrine (qadam-gāh) of Bahā’ al-Dīn [Naqshband] from when
            he was on pilgrimage (ziyārat) to the shrine of ʿAbd al-Khāliq. Halting a fourth of a
            Farsakh from the village of Unf al-Bayān, on the way back from the pilgrimage, every
            person travelling from Bukhara to Ghijduvan can see the sacred footprints at the
            aforementioned mulberry tree.</ts>
    </loc_sec>
    <loc_sec id="48">
        <heading>Wabkand</heading>
        <ts>The third province of Bukhara is the province of Kamat, i.e. Wabkand. The province
            (tūmān) of Kamat is better known as Wabkand</ts>
        <ts>The bazar [Wabkand] is rich and prosperous, and the weather of the province is
            good.</ts>
        <ts>In terms of remnants of ancient ruins, there is a stone minaret built by Arp Aslan Khan
            [a Seljuk ruler], who built it in the year 455 hijri [1063-1064 CE]. The mosque of that
            [minaret] was destroyed by an earthquake (ḥarakat-i arż). Now there is a five-prayer
            mosque located nearby the [old] minaret, as well as a stone madrasa, and a partial sufi
            lodge with numerous dorms (ḥujrāt) next to the shrine of Mir Khurd.</ts>
        <ts>In terms of other ancient remnants, the ruins of
            <flag>Shar Narchaq</flag>
             are also located in this province, a half-Farsakh from the district center.</ts>
        <ts>Most of the denizens of this region are merchants or otherwise well off.</ts>
        <ts>The agriculture of this province is also good.</ts>
        <ts>In this province there are three thousand households of descendants of the original
            Muslim conquerors (mujāhidīn-i Islām), from the Arab Najib tribe.
            <flag>revisit</flag>
        </ts>
        <ts>This province has four hundred and sixty mosques and twelve sufi lodges (khānaqāh-i
            ʿaydayn wa jumaʿa khwānī).</ts>
        <ts>The total number of residents of this province is fifty thousand households. Of the
            Turkic tribes, the Manghits, the Saray, and the Nayman are many in this province. And
            there are also Tajiks.</ts>
        <ts>According to local lore, Abu Ali Ibn Sina was from the village of Narchaq. Others say he
            was from
            <flag>check name</flag>
             . However, according to the book Rawżat al-Ṣafāʾ [Ibn Sina] was from a village to the
            south of Bukhara.</ts>
    </loc_sec>
</translation>
