

<?xml-model href="../rsrc/schema/gazetteer_schema_translation.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>


<translation>
    <loc_sec id="47">
        <heading>Qarakol Province</heading>
        <ts type="geography">The second <glossed>
                <target>province</target>
                <gloss type="translit">wilāyat ū ḥukūmat</gloss>
            </glossed> of the provinces of Bukhara is the <glossed>
                <target>district</target>
                <gloss type="translit">qaẓā</gloss>
            </glossed> of Qarakol. Its distance from Bukhara the Noble is seven <glossed>
                <target>farsakhs</target>
                <gloss type="comment">A "farsakh" is an old Persian unit of measurement, around 4
                    miles.</gloss>
            </glossed>.</ts>
        <ts type="lore">This province is vast and populous. The denizens of this province are all well-off, and
            all of them <glossed>
                <target>have livestock</target>
                <gloss type="literal">have herds</gloss>
            </glossed>. In the past, this province was even vaster; [but then] in the span of a
            century, sand enveloped a quarter of the province from the west, north, and south.
            Nevertheless, [Qarakol is among] the most propserous of the provinces. Due to a <glossed>
                <target>lack of learning</target>
                <gloss type="translit">ʿadam-i ʿilm</gloss>
            </glossed>, the population does not engage in trade. However, in this province there are
            many individuals who own more than one or two million <glossed>
                <target>Tanga</target>
                <gloss type="comment">a currency</gloss>
            </glossed>, and many of them are even wealthier than the Bukharan merchants. Qarakol
            [sheep] skins are well known for their high value, and are even more prized in <glossed>
                <target>Europe</target>
                <gloss type="translit">Ūrūpā ū Farangistān</gloss>
            </glossed> than in Bukhara, and are obtainable in greater numbers and earlier [in the
            season] than in other provinces.</ts>
        <ts type="economic">In this province there is: one <glossed>
                <target>brick and mortar</target>
                <gloss type="translit">sangīn</gloss>
            </glossed> madrasa and one <glossed>
                <target>qārī-khāna</target>
                <gloss type="comment">Qur'an recitation center</gloss>
            </glossed>; adjacent to the <glossed>
                <target>fortress</target>
                <gloss type="translit">Qurghan</gloss>
            </glossed> are seven <glossed>
                <target>sufi lodges</target>
                <gloss type="translit">khānaqāh</gloss>
            </glossed> (both wooden and stone) and eighteen mosques. [The province] comprises 809
            villages, which contain 150,000 residents. </ts>
        <ts type="infrastructure">Water in this province is inadequate, but despite that, agriculture is good. In a bad
            [drought] year, the land is irrigated, which leads to a strong harvest.</ts>
        <ts type="agricultural">To the west of this province is a <glossed>
                <target>salt mine</target>
                <gloss type="translit">maʿdan-i namak</gloss>
            </glossed>, located four farsakhs <glossed>
                <target>from the center</target>
                <gloss type="translit">az markaz-i qażā-yi ān</gloss>
            </glossed>. Every year around ten thousand individuals beset by <glossed>
                <target>illnesses of the nerves</target>
                <gloss type="translit">amrāż-i ʿaṣabānī</gloss>
            </glossed>, such as <glossed>
                <target>back pain</target>
                <gloss type="translit">ʿirq al-nisā</gloss>
            </glossed>, come to this salt mine for treatment. Even foreigners consider the mineral
            water from this mine to be superior to others.</ts>
        <ts type="nat-resources">To the east of this province, in the territory of <glossed>
                <target>Paykand</target>
                <gloss type="comment">Paykand was indeed a major silk road town destroyed during the
                    Arab conquests.</gloss>
            </glossed>, there is a ruin in the sand. This is in fact the original, ancient city of
            Bukhara, and <glossed>
                <target>Ubaydallah ibn Ziyad</target>
                <gloss type="comment">The text actually identifies this Arab general as ʿAbdallāh
                    ibn Ziyād, but the author surely intended ʿUbaydallāh ibn Ziyād (d. 686), who
                    led the first Arab invasion of Bukhara.</gloss>
            </glossed> fought there. Now all of the <glossed>
                <target>walls and fortresses</target>
                <gloss type="translit">suwar ū qalʿa ū arg</gloss>
            </glossed> and some of the buildings still remain, but - in the words of the holy Qur'an
            - <glossed>
                <target>"and it was an empty and ruined town"</target>
                <gloss type="comment">The longer passge is: "Or such as he who passed by a city that
                    was fallen down upon its turrets; he said, 'How shall God give life to this now
                    it is dead?'" (Q 2:259)</gloss>
            </glossed>. The people of Paykand excavate this area to find silver and gold coins, and
            other old artifacts, and in this manner make their living. The reason for the ruination
            of this province is twofold: first, the Arab armies devastated it during the conquest
            [of the 7th and 8th centuries]; second, sand has enveloped it. For these two reasons,
            the province has fallen into ruin.</ts>
    </loc_sec>
    <loc_sec id="46">
        <heading>Ghijduvan</heading>
        <ts type="geography">The third province is the <glossed>
                <target>district</target>
                <gloss type="translit">qażā</gloss>
            </glossed> of Kharqānrūd. This province of Ghijduvan is an ancient city and great
            land.</ts>
        <ts type="geography">This province is long; it spans from the <glossed>
                <target>plain</target>
                <gloss type="translit">qir (Turkic origin)</gloss>
            </glossed> of Bābā Dūghī to the <glossed>
                <target>hill</target>
                <gloss type="translit">tall</gloss>
            </glossed> of Ghandak. East-West it is nine farsakhs of pasture and farmland.</ts>
        <ts type="infrastructure">Inside the <glossed>
                <target>fortress</target>
                <gloss type="translit">Qurghan</gloss>
            </glossed> there are a number of ancient structures, including a stone bathhouse, as
            well as a stone <glossed>
                <target>sufi lodge</target>
                <gloss type="translit">khānaqāh</gloss>
            </glossed> at the head of the <glossed>
                <target>shrine</target>
                <gloss type="translit">mazār</gloss>
            </glossed> of Shaykh Tāj al-Dīn. Inside the city there are seven other mosques. Also
            inside that city are one thousand households. The cities of Pirmast and Sultanabad run
            right up against the fortress,
            <flag>along which flows a ditch [of water].</flag>
             At the head of the <glossed>
                <target>Abd al-Khaliq shrine</target>
                <gloss type="comment">Shaykh Abd al-Khaliq Ghijduwani's shrine is the first stop of
                    the "seven saints" pilgrimage circuit.</gloss>
            </glossed> at the outskirts of the city there is a <glossed>
                <target>stone madrasa built by Ulugh Beg</target>
                <gloss type="comment">This madrasa built by the famous Timurid prince still
                    stands.</gloss>
            </glossed>.</ts>
        <ts type="ethnographic">Most of the people are Kazakhs of Nur-Ata who come to this province to work; they do not
            go to Bukhara itself. </ts>
        <ts type="lore">The people of this province are constantly injured by <glossed>
                <target>fireworks</target>
                <gloss type="translit">bi-ātash-bāzī ū mūshak-andāzī</gloss>
            </glossed> during the holidays . Every year several individuals are killed or injured.
            Nevertheless, they persist in this activity;
            <flag>despite their learnedness [in this city], they devote great foolishness to this
                pursuit.</flag>
        </ts>
        <ts type="infrastructure">Across five hundred and sixty villages there are 715 mosques and twenty-six
            congregational mosques. </ts>
        <ts type="sacred">In the village of Bāy-Khātūn, at the fut of a great mulberry tree on the road to
            Bukhara, there is a <glossed>
                <target>footprint shrine</target>
                <gloss type="translit">qadam-gāh</gloss>
            </glossed> of Bahā’ al-Dīn [Naqshband] from when he was on <glossed>
                <target>pilgrimage</target>
                <gloss type="translit">ziyārat</gloss>
            </glossed> to the shrine of ʿAbd al-Khāliq. Halting a fourth of a Farsakh from the
            village of Unf al-Bayān, on the way back from the pilgrimage, every person travelling
            from Bukhara to Ghijduvan can see the sacred footprints at the aforementioned mulberry
            tree.</ts>
    </loc_sec>
    <loc_sec id="48">
        <heading>Wabkand</heading>
        <ts type="geography">The third province of Bukhara is the province of Kamat, i.e. Wabkand. The <glossed>
                <target>province</target>
                <gloss type="translit">tūmān</gloss>
            </glossed> of Kamat is better known as Wabkand</ts>
        <ts type="lore">The bazar [Wabkand] is rich and prosperous, and the weather of the province is
            good.</ts>
        <ts type="infrastructure">In terms of remnants of ancient ruins, there is a stone minaret built by <glossed>
                <target>Arp Aslan Khan</target>
                <gloss type="comment">A famous Seljuk sultan (r. 1063-1072)</gloss>
            </glossed>, who built it in the year 455 hijri [1063-1064 CE]. The mosque of that
            [minaret] was destroyed by an <glossed><target>earthquake</target><gloss type="translit">ḥarakat-i arż</gloss></glossed>. Now there is a five-prayer
            mosque located nearby the [old] minaret, as well as a stone madrasa, and a partial sufi
            lodge with numerous <glossed><target>dorms</target><gloss type="translit">ḥujrāt</gloss></glossed> next to the shrine of Mir Khurd.</ts>
        <ts type="infrastructure">In terms of other ancient remnants, the ruins of
            <flag>Shar Narchaq</flag>
             are also located in this province, a half-farsakh from the district center.</ts>
        <ts type="economic">Most of the denizens of this region are merchants or otherwise well off.</ts>
        <ts type="agricultural">The agriculture of this province is also good.</ts>
        <ts type="ethnographic">In this province there are three thousand households of descendants of the original
            <glossed><target>Muslim conquerors</target><gloss type ="translit">mujāhidīn-i Islām</gloss></glossed>, from the Arab Najib tribe. [In all], this
            province has five hundred and nine villages.</ts>
        <ts type="sacred">This province has four hundred and sixty mosques and twelve <glossed><target>sufi lodges</target><gloss type="translit">khānaqāh-i
            ʿaydayn wa jumaʿa khwānī</gloss></glossed>.</ts>
        <ts type="ethnographic">The total number of residents of this province is fifty thousand households. Of the
            Turkic tribes, the Manghits, the Saray, and the Nayman are many in this province. And
            there are also Tajiks.</ts>
        <ts type="lore">According to local lore, Abu Ali Ibn Sina was from the village of Narchaq. Others say he
            was from
            <flag>[a different village]</flag>
             . However, according to the book Rawżat al-Ṣafāʾ [Ibn Sina] was from a village to the
            south of Bukhara.</ts>
    </loc_sec>
</translation>
